# 嗨喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 上次我们不是做了腊鱼吗
Last time we made some cured fish
# 这个腊鱼后面抹了一些辣椒还有花椒
There are some chili and Sichuan peppercorns on it
# 因为四川都要吃辣嘛
You know, everyone eats chilis in Sichuan
# 现在准备拿一条弄来吃一下
Now we are going to have one of the fish
# 看一下味道怎么样
See how it tastes
# 冬天了是吃香腊 这个腊味的时候了
It’s winter now. It’s the season for enjoying cured food
# 噶 四伯爷
Right, uncle?
# 嗯 是按
Hmm, yeah
# 吃来试哈看嘛 看安不安逸嘛
Let’s have a try, see if it’s nice
# 煮一条就是哈
Cook one of them?
# 啊整一条嘛 少整点来试一哈看
Ah, just one. Not too much, just have a try
# 要得
Sure
# 这个鱼弄开 把这个割开
Open the fish, and cut this
# 先把它放到锅里面煮一下
Need to boil it first
# 但是我现在先配一下料
But I got to prepare the other stuff
# 这个先放这边哈
Leave it here first
# 这个料非常简单
It’s very simple
# 就是姜跟蒜
Only ginger and garlic
# 你不拿花（椒） 不用花椒吗
You don’t take pep… No Sichuan peppercorns?
# 昂
Huh?
# 不拿花椒吗
You don’t need Sichuan peppercorns?
# 要
I do
# 对咯
That’s right
# 这个姜蒜稍微多一点
Need a bit more ginger and garlic
# 一起剁碎了就行了
Just mince everything together
# 这个做法是贵州 就是我老婆她们那边
This is a Guizhou recipe. It’s from my wife’s hometown
# 少数民族的一种做法
From the ethnic minorities there
# 他们喜欢这样子做的话是因为这个姜蒜
They prefer this recipe, as they
# 下锅爆香了之后加那个干辣椒
fry the ginger and garlic to fragrant, and then add dried chili
# 然后再跟那个鱼一起炒
and stir fry with the fish
# 炒香了再用来蒸
and finally steam it
# 把这个姜蒜的香味蒸到鱼里面去
so that the flavor of garlic and ginger is steamed into the fish
# 好了
Alright
# 所以一般会多一些
So we need more of these
# 少数民族的做法
This is an ethnic recipe
# 然后再切点这个干辣椒
Then we chop some dried chili
# 干辣椒切开就行了
Just chop it like this
# 其实干辣椒用刀切比用剪刀更快
In fact, chopping is more efficient than cutting with scissors
# 我还准备了一些这个辣椒面跟花椒粉
I also prepared some chili powder and Sichuan pepper powder
# 今天的猪肉好不好卖哦四伯爷
How’s your pork business today, uncle?
# 今天没卖
No business today
# 今天休息啊
Closed today?
# 休息
Closed
# 我以为你今天赶场去了
I thought you went to the market
# 每天赶三道场太累了 休息一天
It’s too tiring to work in three markets everyday. I’m taking a day off
# 干两天休息一天
Work for two days, then rest for one day
# 这个火现在起来了我要加点水
Now the fire is on, I’ll add some water
# 把这个鱼放下去先煮个十分钟
Put the fish in and boil for 10 minutes
# 把它的一些盐味啊咸味啊还有一些辣味啊
To get rid of the saltiness, spiciness
# 还有一些不好的味道先除一下味
and some other unpleasant tastes. To reduce them
# 你这个瓜瓢都用了很多年了噶
You’ve been using this scoop for quite many years?
# 田土下户你想哈看
Since the 1980s. Think about it! # 家庭联产承包责任制什么的太难解释了，算了吧...
# 煮腊肉一般我们冷水下锅更好一些
To boil cured meat, it’s better to start with cold water
# 冷水下锅更容易煮透 是噶
That makes it easier to cook through
# 因为我们农村这个腊鱼腊肉咸味都会稍微重一些
Our countryside homemade cured fish and pork are typically very salty
# 所以就先放水里面煮一次
so we boil it in water first
# 煮完了之后再用这个姜蒜辣椒
After boiling, we season it again with
# 还有这个花椒面一起再重新调味
ginger, garlic, chili and Sichuan pepper powder
# 再放点白糖中和一下
And neutralize it with some sugar
# 最后再放到锅里面蒸
And finally steam it
# 四伯爷 你说你小时候非凡
Uncle, you said you were “extraordinary” when you were young
# 有好凡呢
How extraordinary was it?
# 哎呀 啥样都干过
Eiya, I’ve done all kinds of things
# 啥样都干过
You’ve done all kinds of things?
# 哦 啥样都干过
Yeah, everything
# 比如呢
For example?
# 烧锅锅酒儿（过家家）啊
Playing grown up
# 得屠场头割肉啊
Taking meat from the slaughterhouse
# 人家的边口（猪肉）搭得那板板高头及
They left those “biankou” (pork) on some tall platforms
# 一爪就把人家的腰子给人家逮（拿）了
I reached out and grabbed the kidney
# 逮起出去烧锅锅酒儿
Grabbed it to play grown up
# 伯娘那哈说你留长头发多帅的噶
Aunt said you had long hair before, which was cool then?
# 嗯 是啊
Hmm, yeah
# 那哈照身份证的时候拿钢夹（发夹）锁起来照
At that time, when taking my ID photo, I got to use a hair clip
# 照那个时候
when taking the photo
# 你是咋子追的四伯娘
How did you marry aunt?
# 哎呀 那个时候
Eiya… At that time
# 我们认到就是那哈儿最初那个田土下放的时候
We met each other in 1980s, when we got the fields
# 买起电影机子看电影
We bought a movie machine to watch movies
# 就看那个天仙配
We watched Tian Xian Pei (aka Fairy Couple)
# 啊
Ah
# 就看了连续我就看了七场
I watched it for 7 times in a row
# 好 那哈子才想耍朋友了
Then I realized I needed a girlfriend
# 否则还没得那个感觉得
Otherwise, I had no such idea in my mind
# 诶 那个天仙配看了来启发了我
Eh, so apparently the movie inspired me
# 不是的话 我都还是光棍
Otherwise, I’m still single
# 司令还是个 光棍司令是个
Lonely single man # 这个实在没法翻译...
# 这个鱼快要熟了
The fish is almost cooked
# 辣椒面都浮起来了
The chili powder is already floating
# 其实这个辣椒面它腌鱼的话就不是说用来一直让它在肉里面
Actually, when curing fish with chili powder, you don’t need it to stay in the fish
# 这个就是取它的味道
You just need the flavor
# 好了 四伯爷先不忙放柴了
Alright, uncle, no more firewoods for now
# 这个鱼要得了
The fish is done
# 我拿起去砍
I’ll chop it
# 哇 这个鱼还不是特别干
Wow, the fish isn’t very dry yet
# 要是再干一点的话肯定会更香一些
It should be more flavorful if it has become drier
# 我拿起去砍去了
I’ll take it to chop
# 要得 这哈子就不烧（火）咯
OK. You don’t need the fire now?
# 暂时不烧
Not for now
# 这条鱼还没 还没到时间所以有一点嫩
This fish hasn’t been preserved for long enough, so it’s still a bit soft
# 不管它 先砍来尝一下味道
Never mind. Chop it and have a try
# 好
Alright
# 现在放一点点油
Add a little bit oil
# 这个可以稍微多那么一点点
Can be a little bit more
# 其实做鱼的话还是要这个菜油更香哈
For fish, it’s rapeseed oil that gives the best flavor?
# 吃鱼不是菜油不好吃 有些拿那个植物油来煎起就不安逸
Must use rapeseed oil for fish. Vegetable oil doesn't taste as good
# 好了 这个油已经在冒大烟了
Alright, the oil is smoking a lot
# 说明这个菜籽油已经熟了
which means the rapeseed oil is already cooked
# 现在放点花椒
Now add in some Sichuan peppercorns
# 再放这个干辣椒爆一下
And add in some dried chili and fry
# 再放这个姜蒜粒
And diced ginger garlic
# （火）小滴点儿的 四伯爷
Lower fire, uncle
# 才两三根柴呢 两根都不够
There are just two fire logs. Not even two
# 炒到这个姜蒜粒香了之后再放这个辣椒面
When the diced ginger and garlic turns fragrant, add in the chili powder
# 辣椒面是出颜色的 也是出香味的
Chili powder gives both the color and the flavor
# 可以稍微多一点
We can use some more
# 少整点 多很了辣得很哦
Enough, it will be too spicy
# 不关事 这个是蒸的
Doesn’t matter. This is steamed
# 这个蒸的都辣
Steamed is also spicy
# 好嘛
OK
# 稍微小滴点儿的 四伯爷 火
A bit lower, uncle. The fire
# 然后放这个鱼下去炒
Then add in the fish and stir fry
# 因为这个鱼可能有一点嫩
As the fish is very delicate
# 所以翻动的时候轻一点
the maneuver should be gentle
# 我们这个调味只放白糖
We only use white sugar fo seasoning
# 因为这个是腊鱼 放白糖可以压住它的咸味
White sugar neutralizes the saltiness in the cured fish
# 再放一点花椒面
Also a little Sichuan pepper powder
# 花椒面可以稍微多一些
Can be a little more
# 等它炒匀了就可以起锅了
Toss it evenly, and then we can plate it
# 好 炒匀了就起锅
Alright, it’s even. Let’s plate it
# 直接就放到这个碗里面
Just put it into this bowl
# 这个鱼非常的香 又香又入味
The fish is so fragrant. Fragrant and flavorful
# 现在我们把这个盖上蒸一会儿
Now let’s cover it and steam it for a while
# 让它那个菜油充分的把这个香味蒸到鱼里面
So that the rapeseed oil carries all the flavors into the fish
# 大概十分钟
About 10 minutes
# 最后出来的时候就撒上葱花就可以了
And finally top it with some chopped green onion before serving
# 现在已经蒸了十多分钟了 差不多了
Ten minutes now. Should be there
# 我看哈看
Let me check
# 哦哟
Oh
# 还多香 蒸起
It smells so good after steaming
# 颜色还多安逸噶
The color looks nice, huh?
# 我尝哈味道怎么样
Let me check how it tastes
# 先整来告（试）哈看
Let me check
# 嗯 这个味道已经融合了
Hmm, the flavors have already fused
# 融合了这个调料的味道
Have already fused the flavors of the seasonings
# 差不多了 我端咯
Should be good now. I’ll take it out
# 烫哦 慢点儿哦
It’s hot. Be careful!
# 不关事
I’m fine
# 诶呀 四伯爷 火就不烧了
Eiya, uncle, we can put out the fire
# 要得
Sure
# 撒点葱花就可以了
Sprinkle some chopped green onion, then it’s good to go
# 四伯爷尝哈不
Have a try, uncle?
# 可以啊
Yeah
# 辣呼辣呼的
Kind of spicy, huh?
# 嗯 安逸
Hmm, nice
# 很要入味噶
Very flavorful, isn’t it?
# 很有好入味 还多
Very flavorful, and...
# 没有放盐巴 就是我觉得咸了一点点
I didn’t add salt. I felt like it’s a bit too salty
# 不关事嘛 咸点不管下烧酒下饭也好都可以撒
I don’t mind. It’s still good with shaojiu (liquor) or rice
# 嗯 要得
Hmm, OK
# 可以可以可以
Good, good, good
# 好 把火熄了嘛
Alright, let’s put out the fire
# 老子要二回多整点
Next time Imma make more of dis
# 嗯 我在那方（饭厅）等你哦
Yeah. Join us in the dining room
# 好嘛好
OK, yeah